Finding Aid for Lucille H. McCollough papers
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Lucille H. McCollough papers 1955-1989, 1965-1982
McCollough, Lucille H.
1 oversize folders
15.5 linear feet
2013075 Aa 2 Ac
Lucille H. McCollough was a Democratic State Representative for the Michigan House of Representatives representing the 16th District (Wayne County) from 1954 to 1964, and the 31st District (Wayne County) from 1964 to 1982. McCollough's papers comprise her legislative work and involvement with issues surrounding education, senior citizens, and property taxes. Collection also highlights many other bills she introduced, her campaign efforts with her son, Senator Patrick McCollough, and her relationships with her constituents.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Donated by Patrick H. McCollough (Donor no. 10865 ) in December 2012.
No further additions to the records are expected.
The collection is open to research.
Lucille Hanna McCollough was born on December 30, 1905 in White Rock, Michigan to William and Stella Hanna. At a young age she became a teacher for a one-room school near White Rock, and in 1924 moved to Detroit where she acquired a job as a secretary. Shortly following her move to Detroit, she married Clarence McCollough and moved to Fordson (now Dearborn). She remained a resident of Dearborn for 70 years, until her death in March 1996. Lucille McCollough had three children: Clarence Jr., Marilyn (Edwards), and Patrick McCollough.
McCollough's political career started when she joined the McDonald's Elementary School Mother's Club and became active in several homeowners associations. In 1949, at a time when it was difficult for women to hold political office, she was elected to the Dearborn City Council and served for two terms. In 1954 she was elected to the Michigan House of Representatives and served for 28 years. Her son, Patrick, followed in her footsteps, and in 1975 became one of Michigan's youngest senators. Lucille and Patrick McCollough made up the first mother-son legislative team in the United States.
McCollough was incredibly active throughout her career. She served on four committees, including a Chairmanship of the House Education Committee where she sought a way to assume the State's responsibility toward an equal educational opportunity for all students. This effort led to her sponsoring McCollough-Bursley School Aid Formula. She was the chief sponsor of Michigan's Mandatory Special Education Law, which was the first of its kind. She was extremely active in Legislative efforts to improve the Public School Employees Retirement System. She also authored the Homestead Tax Exemption Bill (also known as The McCollough Act) and many other bills on behalf of veterans, senior citizens, teachers, school children, and homeowners. After she stopped serving as a State Representative in 1982, she continued to serve as a Senator volunteer for her son, Patrick. Additionally, McCollough was appointed as the Michigan State Commissioner on Services to the Aging.
McCollough served as director and was one of the founders of the Dearborn Federation of Civic Associations. She was secretary and chairman of the Lydia Women's Group of Littlefield Boulevard United Presbyterian Church. Throughout her life McCollough was active in the United Foundation, Dearborn Navy Mothers Club, Ladies Auxiliary of the Veterans of Foreign Wars Post 1494, Women of the Moose, Dearborn Y.M.C.A., League of Women Voters, Dearborn Democratic Club, Women's Benefit Association, and Women's Political Research League.
McCollough has received many awards and recognitions for her legislative work. In 1977 McCollough set a record 100% perfect legislative attendance. She also held the highest voting average in the House of Representatives. In 2002 McCollough was inducted into the Michigan Women's Hall of Fame. An elementary school in Dearborn, Mich. is named after her.
This collection documents the political career of Lucille H. McCollough, her campaign efforts, House bills she introduced, and other activities. Researchers will find correspondence and memoranda, topical files, material related to legislative documents, newsletters and press releases, and campaign material. Collection is organized in four series: Professional Files, Publications, Miscellaneous, and Photographs.
Subjects:
McCollough, Lucille H.; McCollough, Patrick H.; Michigan. Legislature. House of Representatives.; Home ownership--Law and legislation--Michigan.; Legislators--Michigan.; Mental health laws--Michigan.; Older people--Law and legislation--Michigan.; Women politicians--Michigan.; Special education--Law and legislation--Michigan.
Genre Terms:
Photographs.
- Professional Files
  The Professional Files series (14 linear feet) mostly consists of correspondence with constituents and various topical files relating to McCollough's work passing various bills. This series is organized chronologically. Topical files within the sub-series are organized alphabetically because many of them span several years and overlap.
  Researchers will find professional files dated 1955-1961 in Boxes 1-3; 1962-1963 in Box 9; 1965 in Boxes 3-4, 9 and 16; 1966 in Boxes 4-5 and 16; 1967 in Boxes 9-10; 1969-1970 in Boxes 10-11; 1971 in Boxes 11-13 and 16; 1973-1974 in Boxes 13-14 and 16; 1975-1970 in Boxes 5-6 and 14; and professional files dated in the 1980s in Boxes 6-8 and 14-15.
  - Biographies
    - Essays, newspaper clippings (Box 1)
  - 1955
    - Correspondence, 22 folders (Box 1)
      (in alphabetical order)
  - 1956
    - Correspondence, 20 folders (Box 1)
  - 1957
    - Correspondence, 18 folders (Box 1)
    - Appreciation letters (Box 1)
    - Bills signed (Box 1)
    - University of Michigan (Box 1)
      (Ford Motor Company donating money to build the University of Michigan-Dearborn campus)
  - 1958
    - Correspondence, 19 folders (Box 1)
    - Appreciation letters (Box 1)
    - Bills introduced (Box 2)
    - Boys Vocational School (Box 2)
      (funding the construction of a boys rehabilitation facility)
    - Dogs (Box 2)
      (laws to protect trespassing dogs)
    - Fish (Box 2)
      (the Michigan Sportsmen Fishing Law)
    - Public Employee Press, Volume 2, No. 2, March 7, 1958 (Box 2)
  - 1959
    - Correspondence, 21 folders (Box 2)
    - Scooter 1957-1960 1958 (Box 2)
      (age and passenger restrictions for motorcycles)
    - Scooter Bill (Box 2)
      (House Bill No. 43: number of people allowed to ride a motorcycle at one time)
    - Visitors (Box 2)
  - 1960
    - Correspondence, 18 folders (Box 2)
    - Bills Introduced (Box 2)
    - Michigan, My Michigan -- State Song (Box 2)
      (includes materials from 1958)
  - 1961
    - Correspondence, 21 folders (Box 3)
    - Mental Health
      - Children -- mentally ill 1957 (Box 3)
        (newspaper clippings)
      - Department of Mental Health Publications 1960-1962 (Box 3)
      - General 1961-1962, 2 folders (Box 3)
        (includes one letter from 1960)
      - House Bill No. 351 1960 (Box 3)
        (better care of mentally ill children in Michigan State Mental Hospitals)
      - State mental hospitals (Box 3)
  - 1962-1963
    - Correspondence, 23 folders (Box 9)
    - Election-Primary (Box 9)
    - Fox Bounty (Box 9)
    - Homestead Tax Exemption (Box 9)
    - House Bill No. 431 (Box 9)
  - 1965
    - Correspondence, A-M, 11 folders (Box 3)
    - Correspondence, N-Z, 8 folders (Box 4)
    - Visitors (Box 4)
    - Aging Commission (Box 9)
    - Amish (Box 9)
    - House Bills No.
      - 2001 "The McCollough Bill", 2 folders (Box 9)
        (includes photos of signing by Governor Romney)
      - 2419 (Box 9)
      - 3036 (Box 9)
    - Social Aid and Welfare (Box 15)
  - 1965-1966
    - Correspondence
      - General (Box 4)
      - To answer (Box 4)
    - Conservation (Box 4)
    - Education (Box 4)
    - Home Owners 1963-1966, 3 folders (Box 4)
      (homestead tax exemptions for senior citizens)
    - Merger -- reorganization of School Districts (Box 4)
    - Minimum Pensions (Box 4)
    - Press Releases 1964-1966 (Box 4)
    - Safety (Box 4)
    - Senate Bills
      - 272 (Box 4)
      - 780 (Box 4)
    - Senior Citizens 1964-1966 (Box 4)
    - Veterans (Box 4)
    - House Bill No. 2268 (Box 15)
    - Retirement (Box 15)
  - 1966
    - Correspondence
      - General, 17 folders (Box 4)
      - To answer (Box 4)
      - Unsorted, 3 folders (Box 5)
    - 18 year old vote (Box 5)
    - Bills (Box 5)
    - County Home Rule (Box 5)
    - Daycare (Box 5)
    - Education
      - General (Box 5)
      - Bills (Box 5)
      - Detroit schools (Box 5)
      - Senate Bill No. 780 (Box 5)
        (student tuition grants)
    - Endorsement requests (Box 5)
      for re-election
    - House Bills No.
      - 2550 (Box 5)
      - 3327 (Box 5)
      - 2712 and 3381 (Box 5)
      - 4025, 3 folders (Box 5)
    - Kloster, Alexander J. (Box 5)
      (1966 Acting Superintendent of Public Instruction, Department of Education)
    - Legislation (Box 5)
    - Legislative American Federation of Labor and Congress of Industrial Organizations (AFL-CIO) (Box 5)
    - McCollough Act (Box 5)
    - Millennial celebration of the Freemasons (Box 5)
    - Mental health (Box 5)
    - P. Groups (Box 5)
      (mostly invitations and appointments)
    - Pay Raise (Box 5)
    - Retirement -- House Bill No. 2160 (Box 5)
    - School Merger (Box 5)
    - Social Aid and Welfare (Box 5)
    - Taxes (Box 5)
    - Veterans (Box 5)
    - Schools, 2 folders (Box 15)
  - 1967
    - Correspondence, 22 folders (Box 9)
    - Education (Box 9)
    - Homestead Exemption (Box 9)
    - House Bills No.
      - 2261 (Box 9)
      - 2525 (Box 9)
      - 2544 Senate Bill No. 745 (Box 9)
      - 3254 (Box 9)
    - Press Releases (Box 10)
    - Roads (Box 10)
    - Senate Bill No. 1 (Box 10)
  - 1969-1970
    - Correspondence, A-T, 22 folders (Box 10)
    - Correspondence, U-Z, 5 folders (Box 11)
    - Abortion (Box 11)
    - Community Colleges (Box 11)
    - Education
      - General, 2 folders (Box 11)
      - Press Releases (Box 11)
    - Election (Box 11)
    - Endorsements (Box 11)
    - House Bills No.
      - 2001 (Box 11)
      - 2014 (Box 11)
      - 2080 (Box 11)
      - 2117, 2 folders (Box 11)
      - 2231 (Box 11)
      - 2826 (Box 11)
      - 2961 (Box 11)
      - 2995 (Box 11)
      - 3976 (Box 11)
      - 4029 (Box 11)
      - 4139 (Box 11)
      - 4235 (Box 11)
    - School Districting (Box 11)
    - Senate Bills No.
      - 124 (Box 11)
      - 1082, 1084 (Box 11)
      - 1180 (Box 11)
    - Sex Education (Box 11)
    - Special Education (Box 11)
  - 1971
    - Correspondence, A-M, 12 folders (Box 11)
    - Correspondence, N-Z, 11 folders (Box 12)
    - Abortion (Box 12)
    - Community Colleges-Henry Ford (Box 12)
    - Dearborn-City Offices (Box 12)
    - Drug Abuse (Box 12)
    - Education
      - Correspondence (Box 12)
      - Lincoln Park (Box 12)
      - Press Releases (Box 12)
      - State School Aid (Box 12)
    - House Bills No.
      - 4065 (Box 12)
      - 4169 (Box 12)
      - 4194 (Box 12)
      - 4249 (Box 12)
      - 4261 (Box 12)
      - 4316 (Box 12)
      - 4328 (Box 12)
      - 4472 (Box 12)
      - 4575 (Box 12)
      - 5361 (Box 12)
      - 5624 (Box 12)
      - 5717 (Box 12)
      - 5718, 2 folders (Box 12)
    - Press Releases (Box 12)
    - Senate Bills No.
      - 210 (Box 12)
      - 442 (Box 12)
    - White House Conference on Aging (Box 12)
    - Compensatory Education Services (Box 15)
    - House Bills No. (Box 15)
      - 4252 (Box 15)
      - 4813, 2 folders (Box 15)
  - 1972
    - Correspondence, M-O, 2 folders (Box 12)
    - Correspondence, P-Z, 8 folders (Box 13)
    - Equal Rights Amendment (Box 13)
    - General Pulaski Day (Box 13)
    - House Bills No.
      - 4002, 3 folders (Box 13)
      - 4199 (Box 13)
      - 5706, 5707 (Box 13)
      - 6001 (Box 13)
      - 6078 (Box 13)
      - 6087, 6119 (Box 13)
      - 6213 (Box 13)
      - 6222 (Box 13)
      - 6273 (Box 13)
      - 6366 (Box 13)
    - Press Releases (Box 13)
    - School Aid (Box 13)
    - Senate Bills
      - 699 (Box 13)
      - 1106 (Box 13)
      - 1109 (Box 13)
      - 1181, 2 folders (Box 13)
    - Welfare (Box 13)
    - Education Committee (Box 15)
    - Probate Law Revision, 2 folders (Box 15)
  - 1973-1974
    - Correspondence, A-C, 4 folders (Box 13)
    - Correspondence, D-M (Box 14)
      (11 folders)
    - Anderson, Loren (Box 14)
    - Crisis Meeting, Department of Education (Box 14)
    - Dearborn Federation of Teachers (Box 14)
    - Detroit Schools (Box 14)
    - Governor-Appropriations (Box 14)
    - House Bills No.
      - 5101 (Box 14)
      - 5266 (Box 14)
      - 5988 (Box 14)
    - Press Releases (Box 14)
    - Revenue Sharing
      - Dearborn (Box 14)
      - General (Box 14)
    - Senate Bills No.
      - 139 (Box 14)
      - 141 (Box 14)
      - 264 (Box 14)
    - School Aid Materials, 2 folders (Box 15)
    - Senate Bills No.
      - 110, 2 folders (Box 15)
    - Special Education (Box 15)
  - 1975-1979
    - Election 1976-1979 (Box 5)
      (includes Constitution of the State of Michigan, 1978 and The Dearborn Historian Vol. 17 No. 1, Winter 1977 featuring an article on McCollough)
    - Press releases 1977-1979, 2 folders (Box 5)
      (from the Michigan House of Representatives)
    - Senate Bill No. 122 -- School Employees Retirement 1975-1977 (mostly 1976) (Box 6)
    - Solar energy
      - General 1977-1978, 2 folders (Box 6)
      - Press Release -- House Bill No. 5153, 1979 (Box 6)
    - House Bills No. (Box 14)
      - 4013 1979 (Box 14)
      - 4015 1977-1978 (Box 14)
      - 4016 1977 (Box 14)
      - 4119 1977 (Box 14)
      - 4562 1977 (Box 14)
    - Polybrominated Biphenyl (PBB) 1977-1978 (Box 14)
    - School Aid 1978 (Box 14)
  - 1980s
    - Correspondence
      - 1980-1982 A-L, 13 folders (Box 6)
      - 1980-1982 M, 2 folders (Box 7)
      - 1980-1982 S, 2 folders (Box 7)
      - 1980-1982 N-O, 2 folders (Box 14)
      - 1980-1982 P-R, 3 folders (Box 16)
      - Senator Patrick McCollough 1983 (Box 7)
        (Lucille McCollough as a volunteer Senator Patrick McCollough)
    - Abortion 1980-1982, 2 folders (Box 7)
    - Aging Commission 1981-1982, 2 folders (Box 7)
    - Arts 1980-1982 (Box 7)
      (includes material from 1978-1979)
    - Commission on Services to the Aging -- Appointment 1984-1985 (Box 7)
    - Dearborn 1980-1982 (Box 7)
    - Elections
      - Campaigns 1980-1986 (Box 7)
        (for Patrick and Lucille McCollough)
      - Defeat 1982 (Box 7)
      - Re-election -- Endorsements and Congratulations 1980 (Box 7)
      - Withdrawal 1984 (Box 7)
    - Gasohol 1980-1982 (Box 8)
    - Gene Caesar-Education 1982, 3 folders (Box 8)
    - Guinness Record 1981-1982 (Box 8)
    - Hollander House 1980-1982 (Box 8)
      (group home for mentally ill adults)
    - Legislature 1981-1982 (Box 8)
    - Miscellaneous 1980-1989 (Box 8)
    - Press Releases 1980-1982 (Box 8)
    - Reuter 1982 (Box 8)
    - Senior Citizens and Aging 1982-1987
- Publications
  The Publications series (0.1 linear feet) includes newsletters and press releases regarding McCollough's work in the Michigan House of Representatives, as well as articles she wrote for the Michigan School Board Journal and Michigan PTA Bulletin.
  - "Legislative Actions and Priorities" by Lucille McCollough Michigan School Board Journal Vol. 20 No. 10, December 1973 (Box 8)
  - "The Legislature and the Schools (a Role too Often Overlooked)" by Lucille McCollough Michigan PTA Bulletin, November 1978 (Box 8)
  - "The Mandatory Special Education Act-The Added Costs and Benefits of Special Education" by Lucille McCollough Michigan School Board Journal Vol. 23 No. 8, October 1976 (Box 8)
  - Michigan House of Representatives press releases 1960-1979 (Box 8)
  - Michigan Legislative Report, 1970-1982 (Box 8)
    (Newsletter written by Lucille McCollough)
- Miscellaneous
  The Miscellaneous series (0.2 linear feet) includes Campaign Memorabilia and Scrapbooks.
  - Scrapbooks
    - Lucille McCollough 1968-1987 (Box 8)
    - Lucille McCollough Achievements 1966-1985 (Box 8)
    - Senator Patrick McCollough 1973-1987 (Box 8)
  - Campaign Memorabilia (Folder AC)
    (for Lucille and Patrick McCollough)
- Photographs
  The Photographs series (0.2 linear feet) consists of photographs of Lucille and Patrick McCollough, primarily attending various political events. Many of these photographs have been removed from scrapbooks.
  - 1950s (Box 16)
  - 1961-1965 (Box 16)
  - 1967 (Box 16)
  - 1968-1969 (Box 16)
  - 1970-1971 (Box 16)
  - 1973 (Box 16)
  - 1976 (Box 16)
  - 1977 (Box 16)
  - 1978 (Box 16)
  - 1979 (Box 16)
  - 1980-1982 (Box 16)
  - 1986-1987 (Box 16)
  - undated (Box 16)